Principal Engineer & Director, Autonomous Agents Lab

About me

Managing international R&D teams to transform research results into impactful solutions that land in products and services. I am a big open source advocate, creating new strategies to balance software openness and business revenue.

E-mail: germanros1987@gmail.com Web: http://germanros.net

Google scholar: https://scholar.google.es/citations?user=-qGCJfsAAAAJ

Citizen of Spain. US Green Card Holder.

Work Experience

2021-Present Director, Autonomous Agents Lab, Intel, Santa Clara, CA.

- Managing an international and distributed research lab (+10 direct reports) to pivot from pure research to applied research, targeting direct business impact (revenue), in the space of 3D AI, Simulation for AI, Digital Twins, and Sim-to-Real.
- \circ Leading research collaborations with academia and industry partners, producing shared IP (+10 IDFs, +5 publications).
- o Creating new corporate channels to deliver research results to products and services within 2 quarters.
- \circ Leading the creation of new products in the spaces of AI, 3D Content Creation, and Simulation platforms with an estimated revenue of +200 M USD.
- o Leading the R&D strategy for Digital Twins, Simulation for AI, and 3D Content Creation solutions.
- o Active mentor of researchers and engineers.

2021-Present Principal Investigator, DARPA RACER-SIM, Intel, Santa Clara, CA.

- Managing an international consortium (Intel, The University of Texas at Austin, Computer Vision Center,) with +30 headcounts to create the next generation of simulation solutions in the space of off-road ground robots for the US Department of Defense.
- o Leading the technical development of new real-time terramechanics simulation algorithms using machine learning.
- o Leading the technical development of new Digital Twins solutions for large off-road environments.

2019–2020 Program Lead, Advanced simulation solutions for AD, Intel-General Motors, Santa Clara, CA.

- Managed an international and distributed team to create new simulation solutions to enable the training and validation of autonomous driving systems for General Motors.
- o Created shared IP in the space of Simulation for Autonomous Systems and Digital Twins.

2018–2020 Co-founder, OSVF.org: Open Source Vision Foundation, OSVF.org, Palo Alto.

- Created a non-profit organization to drive the growth of open-source projects in the space of AI, Computer Vision, and Simulation.
- o Raised +3M USD in funding over 2 years through sponsorships and contracts.
- \circ Grew a team of +20 engineers to develop new solutions based on open-source projects (e.g., CARLA).

2018–2021 Sr. Staff Scientist, Intel Labs, Santa Clara, CA.

- Served as the program lead for 3D Vision, driving research and technology transfer of novel solutions in the space of 3D Scene Understanding and 3D Reconstruction.
- Served as the program lead for Simulation for Autonomous Systems, creating new solutions to accelerate and standardize the training and validation of autonomous systems. Helped 7+ industry partners to solve problems in the space of Autonomous Systems through simulation.
- o Drove the creation of large communities around open-source projects such as CARLA (from 0 to +200K users) and Open3D (from 100 to +150K users). CARLA is now considered the top-1 autonomous driving simulator, widely used in academia, industry, and government institutions (e.g., DOT, DOE, DOD). Open3D was designated by the Python community as a critical project (top 1% project in downloads over 6 months).
- o Developed new Al-powered techniques in the space of sensor simulation, physics simulation, and Sim-to-Real.

2017–2018 Research Scientist, Toyota Research Institute, Los Altos, CA.

- $\circ\,$ Carried out research in computer vision for Autonomous Driving and Sim-to-Real technologies.
- Created and managed the sensor simulation team, providing new simulation tools for the evaluation of autonomous driving systems end-to-end.
- $\,\circ\,$ Served as the coordinator of research collaborations with the University of Michigan.

- 2016 **R&D Contractor**, *Yandex*, Remote.
 - o Developed new algorithms for change detection using deep learning techniques and synthetic data.

Education

- 2011–2016 PhD in Computer Vision (Cum Laude), Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona, CVC, Spain.
- 2011–2012 MSc in Computer Vision and Artificial Intelligence, Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona, Spain.
- 2010-2011 MSc in Computer Vision and Image Analysis, Kingston University of London, UK, 1st class.
- 2005-2010 BSc in Computer Science (Hons., Cum Laude), University of Murcia, Spain, 1st class.

——— Patents

- 2022 Inferring locations of 3D objects in a spatial environment.
- 2021 System and method for system-aware classifiers.
- 2020 Adversarial learning of photorealistic post-processing of simulation with privileged information.
- 2020 Inferring locations of 3D objects in a spatial environment.
- 2020 System and method for generating improved synthetic images.
- 2020 Method and apparatus for a manifold view of space.
- 2020 Systems and methods for conditional image translation.
- 2019 System and method for full-stack verification of autonomous agents.
- 2019 Virtually boosted training.
- 2018 Training constrained deconvolutional networks for road scene semantic segmentation.

Skills

R&D Manager, Leadership, Applied Research & Development, Tech. transference & Productization, 3D Vision, Simulation for Autonomous Systems, Sim-to-Real, Machine Learning, Game engines, Rendering.

Languages

Spanish: Native; English: Proficient user; Catalan: Basic user; Japanese: Basic user

Selected Awards & Honours

- 2021 National Research Award for Public-private Partnership in Research & Innovation, Barcelona, Spain.
- 2016 Honors, Cum Laude PhD Thesis, Barcelona, Spain.
- 2016 Finalist for Best System Paper Award at the Robotics Science and Systems (RSS) conference, Award given by the RSS consortium to outstanding systems papers presented at the RSS conference., Michigan, USA.
- 2010 Honourable mention Computer Science, 1st class, Promotion 2005–2010, Murcia, Spain.
- 2009 **Award of excellence in academic performance**, *Top 10 student of science and mathematics*, Murcia, Spain.

Selected Publications

- K.-H. Lee, G. Ros, J. Li, and A. Gaidon, "SPIGAN: Privileged adversarial learning from simulation," in *International Conference on Learning Representations*, 2019.
- M. R. Anderson, M. Cafarella, G. Ros, and T. F. Wenisch, "Predicate optimization for a visual analytics database," *SySML conference*, 2018.
- A. Dosovitskiy, G. Ros, F. Codevilla, A. Lopez, and V. Koltun, "CARLA: An open urban driving simulator," in *Conference on Robot Learning (CORL)*, (Mountain View, CA, US), 2017.
- P. Alcantarilla, S. Stent, G. Ros, R. Arroyo, and R. Gherardi, "Street-view change detection with deconvolutional networks," in *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), Michigan, USA*, June 2016.
- G. Ros, L. Sellart, J. Materzynska, D. Vazquez, and A. Lopez, "The SYNTHIA dataset: A large collection

of synthetic images for semantic segmentation of urban scenes," in *The IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, (Las Vegas, USA (short oral)), 2016.